<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.oxygenxml.com/docbook/xml/5.0/rng/dbsvg.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    version="5.0">
    <info>
        <title>Scholary Intervention in Automated Collation Software</title>
        <author>
            <personname>Elli Bleeker</personname>
            <affiliation>
                <orgname>Huygens Institute for the History of the Netherlands</orgname>
            </affiliation>
            <affiliation>
                <orgname>Centre for Manuscript Genetics - University of Antwerp</orgname>
            </affiliation>
        </author>
        <author>
            <personname>Ronald Haentjens Dekker</personname>
            <affiliation>
                <orgname>Huygens Institute for the History of the Netherlands</orgname>
            </affiliation>
        </author>
    </info>
    <note>
        <remark>Paper is currently divided into four sections. The section titles are
            provisory.</remark>
    </note>
    <section>
        <title>Introduction</title>
        <note>
            <remark/>
        </note>
        <para>Textual scholars have at their disposal an increasing number of digital tools and
            technologies to examine the genesis of a literary work. We can model or capture a wide
            variety of (complex) textual phenomena, and our analysis of them, in a digital
                transcription.<remark>Define "digital transcription": this ranges from plain text to
                MS Word to TEI/XML. Suggestion: "A 'digital transcription' can be anuything from
                plain text to MS Word and TEI/XML. Unless explicated otherwise, this paper uses the
                term (digital) transcription to refer to a TEI/XML transcription."</remark> This
            transcription can subsequently be processed by various tools for further analysis or
            visualisation. Simply put, transcribing and processing text are forms of translation,
            from one sign system to another. Making a transcription is generally understood to be a
            critical act of editorial interepretation <xref linkend="robinson_1993"/><xref
                linkend="pierazzo_2015"/>, and we can say the same about text processing: a tool
            performs multiple operations on a text, each operation involving a transformation of the
            data. It follows that before we can influence/customize a tool, it is necessary to
            understand its workings and the transformations a text undergoes. This, in turn, can
            lead to a more fitting/adequate/suitable framework to investigate/model a text.</para>
        <para>An interesting area of study, and one that poses some particularly challengeing
            issues, is the automated collation of modern manuscripts. This type of documents often
            contains (heavy) revisions and complex sites of textual variation which are challengeing
            to adequately capture and process in TEI/XML. In short, the genetic orientation to text
            examines a text's development and the creative processes that propegate literary
                invention<remark>[REF Shillingsburg and Van Hulle 2015]</remark>. As the genetic
            orientation studies the processes of writing and revising, it is vital that revisions
            are included in the collation process, so that researchers can study both the revision
            within one document and the revision across document borders. The present paper
            discusses how human interaction with collation algorithms benefits this kind of
            research. This issue has been previously explored in <remark>[REF to paper ESTS
                2016]</remark>, focusing on one characteristic of textual revisions - substitutions
            - where the word order is of importance. The TEI/XML transcriptions of the modern
            manuscripts of Samuel Beckett and Raymond Brulez serve as case studies.</para>
        <para>As  </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Ordered</title>
        <para>Example 1.1:</para>
        <para>Transcription witness A: Helaas, Hij, Shiriar,</para>
        <para>Smart tokenizer:</para>
        <para>&lt;witness id="a">&lt;w>Helaas&lt;/w>&lt;w>, &lt;/w>&lt;w>Hij&lt;/w>&lt;w>,
            &lt;/w>&lt;w>Shiriar&lt;/w>&lt;w>,&lt;/w>&lt;/witness></para>
        <para>Transcription witness B: Helaas hij, Shir&lt;add
            place="supralinear">i&lt;/add>ar,</para>
        <para>Smart tokenizer:</para>
        <para>&lt;witness id="b">&lt;w>Helaas &lt;/w>&lt;w>hij&lt;/w>&lt;w>,
            &lt;/w>&lt;subst>&lt;del>&lt;w>Shirar&lt;/w>&lt;/del>&lt;add>&lt;w>Shiriar&lt;/w>&lt;/add>&lt;/subst>&lt;w>,&lt;/w>&lt;/witness></para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Hierarchy</title>
        <para/>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Unordered Hierarchy</title>
        <para/>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Conclusion</title>
        <para/>
    </section>
    <bibliography>
        <title>Bibliography</title>
        <bibliomixed xml:id="robinson_1993" xreflabel="Robinson and Solopova 1993">Robinson, Peter,
            and Elizabeth Solopova. <quote>Guidelines for the Transcription of Manuscripts of The
                Wife of Bath's Prologue</quote>. <emphasis role="ital">The Canterbury Tales Project
                Occasional Papers</emphasis>, vol. 1 (1993): 19-52. Oxford: Office for Humanities
            Communication, Oxford University Computing Services.</bibliomixed>
        <bibliomixed xml:id="pierazzo_2015" xreflabel="Pierazzo 2015">Pierazo, Elena. <emphasis
                role="ital">Digital Scholarly Editing: Theories, Models and Methods</emphasis>.
            (2015) Surrey: Ashgate, Ltd.</bibliomixed>
        <!--<bibliomixed xml:id="derose_1990" xreflabel="DeRose et al. 1990">DeRose, Steven J., David G.
            Durand, Elli Mylonas, and Allen H. Renear. <quote>What is text, really?</quote>,
                <emphasis role="ital">Journal of computing in higher education</emphasis>, 1.2
            (1990): 3–26. doi:10.1007/BF02941632.</bibliomixed>-->
    </bibliography>

    <!--<bibliography><bibliolist></bibliolist></bibliography>
-->
</article>
